June 2010.
حزيران 2010.
I landed for the first time in Rome, Italy.
هبطت للمرة الأولى في روما، إيطاليا.
I wasn't there to sightsee.
لم أكن هناك بغرض السياحة.
I was there to solve world hunger.
كنت هناك لحل مشكلة المجاعة في العالم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's right.
هذا صحيح.
I was a 25-year-old PhD student
كنت طالبة دكتوراه أبلغ من العمر 25 عاماً
armed with a prototype tool developed back at my university,
مسلحة بأداة نموذجية طورتها سابقاً في جامعتي،
and I was going to help the World Food Programme fix hunger.
وكنت ذاهبة لمساعدة برنامج الأغذية العالمي للقضاء على مشكلة المجاعة.
So I strode into the headquarters building
لذا خطوتُ إلى داخل مبنى المقر
and my eyes scanned the row of UN flags,
وعيناي مرّتا على صف أعلام الأمم المتحدة.
and I smiled as I thought to myself,
و ابتسمتُ وأنا أقولُ لنفسي،
"The engineer is here."
"المهندسة هنا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Give me your data.
أعطني بياناتك الشخصية.
I'm going to optimize everything.
سأقوم بتحسين كل شيء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Tell me the food that you've purchased,
أخبرني عن الطعام الذي اشتريتموه،
tell me where it's going and when it needs to be there,
قل لي إلى أين هو مُرسل و متى يحتاج أن يكون هناك،
and I'm going to tell you the shortest, fastest, cheapest,
و أنا سأقول لك أقصر، أسرع، أرخص
best set of routes to take for the food.
أفضل مجموعة من الطرق لتوصيل الأغذية.
We're going to save money,
سوف نقوم بتوفير المال،
we're going to avoid delays and disruptions,
سوف نقوم بتجنب التأخير والاضطرابات،
and bottom line, we're going to save lives.
وخلاصة القول، سنقوم بإنقاذ الأرواح.
You're welcome.
على الرحب و السعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I thought it was going to take 12 months,
اعتقدت أنه سيستغرق 12 شهراُ،
OK, maybe even 13.
حسناً، ربما حتى 13.
This is not quite how it panned out.
هذا ليس ما حدث تماماً.
Just a couple of months into the project, my French boss, he told me,
خلال شهرين فقط من المشروع، أخبرني رئيسي الفرنسي في العمل،
"You know, Mallory,
"تعلمين، مالوري،
it's a good idea,
إنها فكرة جيدة،
but the data you need for your algorithms is not there.
لكن البيانات التي تحتاجينها للخوارزميات الخاصة بك ليست هناك.
It's the right idea but at the wrong time,
إنها الفكرة الصحيحة في الوقت الخاطئ،
and the right idea at the wrong time
والفكرة الصحيحة في الوقت الخاطئ
is the wrong idea."
هي فكرة خاطئة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Project over.
انتهى المشروع.
I was crushed.
كنتُ محطّمة.
When I look back now
عندما أسترجع الذكريات الآن
on that first summer in Rome
إلى ذلك الصيف الأول في روما
and I see how much has changed over the past six years,
وأرى كم تغيرت خلال الست سنوات الماضية،
it is an absolute transformation.
إنه تحولٌ مطلق.
It's a coming of age for bringing data into the humanitarian world.
حان الوقت لجلب البيانات إلى العالم الإنساني.
It's exciting. It's inspiring.
إنه مبهج، ومثير.
But we're not there yet.
لكننا لسنا هناك بعد.
And brace yourself, executives,
جهّزوا أنفسكم، أيها المدراء التنفيذيون،
because I'm going to be putting companies
لأنني سوف أضع الشركات
on the hot seat to step up and play the role that I know they can.
على المقعد الساخن ليخطوا ويلعبوا الدور الذي أعلم أنه باستطاعتهم،
My experiences back in Rome prove
تجربتي السابقة في روما أثبتت
using data you can save lives.
أنه باستخدام البيانات يمكنكم إنقاذ الأرواح.
OK, not that first attempt,
حسناً، ليس في المحاولة الأولى،
but eventually we got there.
ولكن في نهاية المطاف وصلنا إلى هناك.
Let me paint the picture for you.
اسمحوا لي أن أرسم الصورة لكم.
Imagine that you have to plan breakfast, lunch and dinner
تخيلوا أنه يجب عليكم تخطيط الفطور والغداء والعشاء
for 500,000 people,
من أجل 500,000 شخص،
and you only have a certain budget to do it,
ولديكم ميزانية محددة فقط لفعل ذلك،
say 6.5 million dollars per month.
لنقل 6.5 مليون في الشهر.
Well, what should you do? What's the best way to handle it?
حسناً، ماذا يجب أن تفعلوا؟ ماهي الطريقة الأفضل لإنجاز ذلك؟
Should you buy rice, wheat, chickpea, oil?
هل يجب أن تشتروا الأرز، الحمص، الزيت؟
How much?
ما المقدار؟
It sounds simple. It's not.
يبدو بسيطاً. لا ليس كذلك.
You have 30 possible foods, and you have to pick five of them.
لديك 30 احتمال للطعام، ويجب أن تختار منهم خمسة.
That's already over 140,000 different combinations.
هذه بالفعل أكثر من 140000 تركيبة مختلفة.
Then for each food that you pick,
بعدها لكل طعام تختاره،
you need to decide how much you'll buy,
يجب أن تقرر كم يجب أن تشتري،
where you're going to get it from,
من أين ستحصل عليه،
where you're going to store it,
أين ستقوم بتخزينه،
how long it's going to take to get there.
كم من الوقت سيأخذ ليصل إلى هناك.
You need to look at all of the different transportation routes as well.
كما عليك أن تبحث في جميع طرق النقل.
And that's already over 900 million options.
وهذا يشكّل حتى الآن أكثر من 900 مليون خيار.
If you considered each option for a single second,
إذا أخذت كل خيار بعين الاعتبار لثانية واحدة،
that would take you over 28 years to get through.
سيستغرقك أكثر من 28 سنة لتخطي ذلك،
900 million options.
900 مليون خيار.
So we created a tool that allowed decisionmakers
لذلك اخترعنا أداة لتساعد متخذي القرار
to weed through all 900 million options
لغربلة 900 مليون خيار
in just a matter of days.
بغضون أيامٍ فقط.
It turned out to be incredibly successful.
تبيّن أنها ناجحة بشكل لا يُصدّق.
In an operation in Iraq,
في عملية في العراق،
we saved 17 percent of the costs,
قمنا بتوفير17 بالمئة من التكلفة،
and this meant that you had the ability to feed an additional 80,000 people.
وهذا يعني أنه لديك القدرة على إطعام 80,000 شخص إضافي.
It's all thanks to the use of data and modeling complex systems.
يعود الفضل كله لاستخدام البيانات ونمذجة النظم المعقدة.
But we didn't do it alone.
لكننا لم نفعل هذا لوحدنا.
The unit that I worked with in Rome, they were unique.
الوحدة التي عملت معها في روما، كانت فريدة من نوعها.
They believed in collaboration.
آمنوا بالتعاون.
They brought in the academic world.
أحضروا العالم الأكاديمي.
They brought in companies.
أحضروا شراكات.
And if we really want to make big changes in big problems like world hunger,
و إذا كنا نريد حقاً أن نحدث تغييراً كبيراَ في مشكلة كبيرة كالمجاعة في العالم،
we need everybody to the table.
نحتاج وجود الجميع.
We need the data people from humanitarian organizations
نحتاج إلى أصحاب البيانات الشخصية من المنظمات الإنسانية
leading the way,
أن يقودوا الطريق،
and orchestrating just the right types of engagements
وتنسيق الأنواع المناسبة فقط من التعاقدات
with academics, with governments.
مع الأكاديميين، مع الحكومات.
And there's one group that's not being leveraged in the way that it should be.
وهنالك مجموعة واحدة لم تقم بهذا كما يجب.
Did you guess it? Companies.
هل حزرتم؟ الشركات.
Companies have a major role to play in fixing the big problems in our world.
للشركات دورٌ كبير لتلعبه في القضاء على مشكلة المجاعة في العالم.
I've been in the private sector for two years now.
لقد كنت في القطاع الخاص لمدة سنتين حتى الآن.
I've seen what companies can do, and I've seen what companies aren't doing,
لقد رأيت ما يمكن للشركات أن تفعله، ورأيت ما لا تفعله،
and I think there's three main ways that we can fill that gap:
و أعتقد أنه لدينا ثلاثة طرق رئيسية لسد تلك الفجوة:
by donating data, by donating decision scientists
عبر التبرع بالبيانات، عبر التبرّع بعلماء القرار
and by donating technology to gather new sources of data.
عبر التبرّع بالتكنولوجيا لجمع مصادر جديدة من البيانات.
This is data philanthropy,
هذا هو العمل الخيري للبيانات،
and it's the future of corporate social responsibility.
وهو مستقبل المشاركة في المسؤولية المجتمعية.
Bonus, it also makes good business sense.
إضافة إلى، أنه يقدم فهم تجاري أفضل.
Companies today, they collect mountains of data,
الشركات اليوم، يجمعون جبالاً من البيانات،
so the first thing they can do is start donating that data.
لذا أول ما يمكنهم فعله هو التبرع بتلك البيانات.
Some companies are already doing it.
بعض الشركات تفعل ذلك فعلاً.
Take, for example, a major telecom company.
خذ، على سبيل المثال، شركة الاتصالات الكبرى.
They opened up their data in Senegal and the Ivory Coast
قاموا بفتح بياناتهم في السنغال وساحل العاج
and researchers discovered
واكتشف الباحثون
that if you look at the patterns in the pings to the cell phone towers,
أنكم إذا نظرتم إلى الأنماط في الرنين إلى أبراج الهاتف الخلوي،
you can see where people are traveling.
يمكنكم معرفة إلى أين يسافر الناس.
And that can tell you things like
وهذا يمكنه إخباركم بأشياء مثل
where malaria might spread, and you can make predictions with it.
أين يمكن أن تنتشر الملاريا، ويمكنكم اتخاذ إجراءات لذلك.
Or take for example an innovative satellite company.
أو خذوا على سبيل المثال شركة أقمار صناعية مبتكرة.
They opened up their data and donated it,
قاموا بفتح بياناتهم وتبرعوا بها،
and with that data you could track
ومع هكذا بيانات يمكنكم تعقّب
how droughts are impacting food production.
كيف يؤثّر الجفاف على إنتاج الغذاء.
With that you can actually trigger aid funding before a crisis can happen.
مع ذلك يمكنكم فعلياً تمويل المساعدات قبل حصول الأزمة.
This is a great start.
هذه بداية رائعة.
There's important insights just locked away in company data.
هناك معلومات هامة مقفلة في بيانات شركة.
And yes, you need to be very careful.
ونعم، عليك أن تكون حذراً للغاية.
You need to respect privacy concerns, for example by anonymizing the data.
عليك احترام المخاوف المتعلقة بالخصوصية، مثلاً عن طريق إخفاء البيانات.
But even if the floodgates opened up,
ولكن حتى لو فُتحَ الباب على مصراعيه،
and even if all companies donated their data
وحتى لو تبرعت جميع الشركات بالبيانات الخاصة بها
to academics, to NGOs, to humanitarian organizations,
للأكاديميين، للمنظمات غير الحكومية، للمنظمات الإنسانية،
it wouldn't be enough to harness that full impact of data
فإنه لن يكون كافياً لتسخير هذا التأثير الكامل للبيانات
for humanitarian goals.
لتحقيق الأهداف الإنسانية.
Why?
لماذا؟
To unlock insights in data, you need decision scientists.
لفك القفل عن البيانات، تحتاج إلى علماء القرار.
Decision scientists are people like me.
علماء القرار هم أناس مثلي.
They take the data, they clean it up,
يقومون بأخذ البيانات، وتنظيفها،
transform it and put it into a useful algorithm
تحويلها ووضعها إلى خوارزمية مفيدة
that's the best choice to address the business need at hand.
هذا أفضل خيار لتلبية حاجة الأعمال المتناولة في اليد.
In the world of humanitarian aid, there are very few decision scientists.
في عالم من المساعدات الإنسانية، هناك عدد قليل جداً من علماء القرار.
Most of them work for companies.
معظمهم يعمل لصالح شركات.
So that's the second thing that companies need to do.
لذا هذا هو الشيء الآخر الذي تحتاج الشركات للقيام به.
In addition to donating their data,
بالإضافة للتبرع بالبيانات الخاصة بهم،
they need to donate their decision scientists.
يجب أن يتبرعوا بعلماء القرار الخاصين بهم.
Now, companies will say, "Ah! Don't take our decision scientists from us.
الآن، ستقول الشركات، " أوه! لا تأخذوا علماء القرار منّا
We need every spare second of their time."
نحتاج إلى كل ثانية فائضة من وقتهم."
But there's a way.
ولكن هنالك طريقة.
If a company was going to donate a block of a decision scientist's time,
إذا كان هنالك شركة ستقوم بالتبرع بكتلة من وقت علماء القرار،
it would actually make more sense to spread out that block of time
سيكون بالفعل منطقياً أكثر لنشر تلك الكتلة من الوقت
over a long period, say for example five years.
لفترة طويلة، لنقل على سبيل المثال خمس سنوات.
This might only amount to a couple of hours per month,
هذا قد يعادل بضع ساعات فقط في الشهر،
which a company would hardly miss,
حيث أنه بالكاد ستفتقده الشركة،
but what it enables is really important: long-term partnerships.
ولكن ما تمكّنه حقاً مهم: شراكة طويلة الأمد،
Long-term partnerships allow you to build relationships,
الشراكات طويلة الأمد تسمح لك ببناء علاقات،
to get to know the data, to really understand it
والتمكن من معرفة البيانات، لتفهمها جيداً
and to start to understand the needs and challenges
وأن تبدأ بفهم الاحتياجات والتحديات
that the humanitarian organization is facing.
التي تواجهها المنظمات الإنسانية.
In Rome, at the World Food Programme, this took us five years to do,
في روما، في برنامج الغذاء العالمي، احتجنا خمس سنوات للقيام بهذا،
five years.
خمس سنوات.
That first three years, OK, that was just what we couldn't solve for.
تلك السنوات الأولى الثلاثة، حسناً، كان ذلك ما لم نستطع حلّه.
Then there was two years after that of refining and implementing the tool,
ثمّ كان هنالك سنتان بعد ذلك، من صقل وتنفيذ هذه الأداة،
like in the operations in Iraq and other countries.
كما هو الحال في عمليات في العراق وبلدان أخرى.
I don't think that's an unrealistic timeline
لا أعتقد أن هذا جدول زمني غير واقعي
when it comes to using data to make operational changes.
عندما يتعلق الأمر باستخدام البيانات لإدخال تغييرات عملية.
It's an investment. It requires patience.
إنه استثمار. يتطلب الصبر.
But the types of results that can be produced are undeniable.
ولكن أنواع النتائج التي يمكن إنتاجها هي التي لا يمكن إنكارها.
In our case, it was the ability to feed tens of thousands more people.
في حالتنا، كانت الإمكانية لإطعام عشرات الآلاف من الناس.
So we have donating data, we have donating decision scientists,
لذا قمنا بالتبرع بالبيانات، قمنا بالتبرع بعلماء القرار،
and there's actually a third way that companies can help:
وهناك بالفعل طريقة ثالثة يمكن للشركات أن تساعد بها:
donating technology to capture new sources of data.
التبرع بالتكنولوجيا لالتقاط مصادر جديدة للبيانات.
You see, there's a lot of things we just don't have data on.
كما ترون، هناك الكثير من الأشياء نحن فقط لا نملك بيانات عنها.
Right now, Syrian refugees are flooding into Greece,
الآن، اللاجئون السوريون يتدفقون إلى اليونان،
and the UN refugee agency, they have their hands full.
وكالة الأمم المتحدة للاجئين، أيديهم مقيّدة بالكامل.
The current system for tracking people is paper and pencil,
النظام الحالي لتتبع الناس هو مجرد ورقة وقلم،
and what that means is
ما يعنيه هذا
that when a mother and her five children walk into the camp,
أنه عندما تسير أم وأطفالها الخمسة إلى المخيم،
headquarters is essentially blind to this moment.
فإن المقر الرئيسي بشكل أساسي أعمى إلى هذه اللحظة.
That's all going to change in the next few weeks,
هذا كله سيتغير في الأسابيع القليلة القادمة،
thanks to private sector collaboration.
وذلك بفضل تعاون القطاع الخاص.
There's going to be a new system based on donated package tracking technology
سيكون هناك نظاماً جديداً يستند على حزمة تكنولوجيا التعقب المتبرع بها
from the logistics company that I work for.
من شركة خدمات اللوجستية التي أعمل لصالحها.
With this new system, there will be a data trail,
مع هذا النظام الجديد، سيكون هناك درب للبيانات
so you know exactly the moment
لكي تعلم اللحظة بالضبط
when that mother and her children walk into the camp.
التي تدخل فيها الأم مع أطفالها إلى المخيم.
And even more, you know if she's going to have supplies
وأكثر، ستعلم إذا كانت ستحصل على إمدادات
this month and the next.
هذا الشهر والذي يليه.
Information visibility drives efficiency.
يقود وضوح المعلومات الكفاءة.
For companies, using technology to gather important data,
بالنسبة للشركات، استخدام التكنولوجيا لجمع البيانات المهمة،
it's like bread and butter.
هو شيء أساسي.
They've been doing it for years,
كانوا يقومون به لسنوات.
and it's led to major operational efficiency improvements.
وأدى إلى إدخال تحسينات ضخمة ذات كفاءة عملية.
Just try to imagine your favorite beverage company
فقط حاول تخيل شركة المشروبات المفضلة لديك
trying to plan their inventory
تحاول التخطيط لجرد خاص بها
and not knowing how many bottles were on the shelves.
ولا تعلم عدد الزجاجات التي كانت على الرفوف.
It's absurd.
إنه غريب.
Data drives better decisions.
تؤدي البيانات إلى خيارات أفضل.
Now, if you're representing a company,
الآن، إذا كنت تمثل شركة،
and you're pragmatic and not just idealistic,
وأنت واقعي ولست فقط مثالي،
you might be saying to yourself, "OK, this is all great, Mallory,
ربما ستقول لنفسك، "حسناً، هذا كله رائع، مالوري،
but why should I want to be involved?"
ولكن لماذا يجب أن أريد المشاركة؟"
Well for one thing, beyond the good PR,
حسنا لشيء واحد، وراء العلاقات العامة الجيدة،
humanitarian aid is a 24-billion-dollar sector,
المساعدات الإنسانية هي قطاع 24 مليار دولار،
and there's over five billion people, maybe your next customers,
وهناك أكثر من خمسة مليارات نسمة، ربما العميل المقبل الخاص بك،
that live in the developing world.
يعيش في العالم النامي.
Further, companies that are engaging in data philanthropy,
وعلاوة على ذلك، فإن الشركات التي تتعاطى في العمل الخيري للبيانات،
they're finding new insights locked away in their data.
تجد رؤى جديدة محبوسة في بياناتهم الخاصة.
Take, for example, a credit card company
خذ، على سبيل المثال، شركة بطاقات الائتمان
that's opened up a center
فتحت مركزاً
that functions as a hub for academics, for NGOs and governments,
الذي يعمل كمركز للأكاديميين، للمنظمات غير الحكومية والحكومات،
all working together.
كلها تعمل معاً.
They're looking at information in credit card swipes
يبحثون عن المعلومات عند استخدام بطاقة الائتمان
and using that to find insights about how households in India
ويستخدمون ذلك لإيجاد رؤى حول الحياة الأسرية في الهند
live, work, earn and spend.
الحياة، العمل، الكسب، والإنفاق.
For the humanitarian world, this provides information
للعالم الإنساني، هذا يزوّد بالمعلومات
about how you might bring people out of poverty.
عن كيفية إخراج الناس من براثن الفقر.
But for companies, it's providing insights about your customers
ولكن بالنسبة للشركات، إنها تقدم رؤى حول الزبائن
and potential customers in India.
والعملاء المحتملين في الهند.
It's a win all around.
إنه فوز على جميع الجهات.
Now, for me, what I find exciting about data philanthropy --
الآن، بالنسبة لي، ما أجده مثيراً حول العمل الخيري للبيانات -
donating data, donating decision scientists and donating technology --
التبرع بالبيانات، التبرع بعلماء القرار والتبرع بالتكنولوجيا -
it's what it means for young professionals like me
إنه ما يعني للمهنيين الشباب مثلي
who are choosing to work at companies.
الذين اختاروا العمل لحساب شركات.
Studies show that the next generation of the workforce
أظهرت الدراسات أن الجيل القادم من القوى العاملة
care about having their work make a bigger impact.
يهتمون بكون عملهم يحدث تأثيراً أكبر.
We want to make a difference,
نريد أن نُحدث فرقاً،
and so through data philanthropy,
وذلك من خلال العمل الخيري للبيانات،
companies can actually help engage and retain their decision scientists.
يمكن للشركات أن تساعد فعلاً بالمشاركة وأن تحتفظ بعلماء القرار خاصتهم.
And that's a big deal for a profession that's in high demand.
وهذه صفقة كبيرة لمهنة تتسم بارتفاع الطلب.
Data philanthropy makes good business sense,
العمل الخيري للبيانات يجعل الإدراك التجاري جيد،
and it also can help revolutionize the humanitarian world.
ويمكن أن يساعد أيضاً في تغيير جذري في العالم الإنساني.
If we coordinated the planning and logistics
إذا قمنا بتنسيق التخطيط والخدمات اللوجستية
across all of the major facets of a humanitarian operation,
عبر جميع الجوانب الرئيسية من عملية إنسانية،
we could feed, clothe and shelter hundreds of thousands more people,
يمكننا تأمين الطعام والكساء والمأوى لمئات الآلاف من المزيد من الناس،
and companies need to step up and play the role that I know they can
ويتعين على الشركات أن تصعد وتلعب الدور الذي أعلم أنه بوسعهم
in bringing about this revolution.
في إحداث هذا التغيير.
You've probably heard of the saying "food for thought."
ربما كنت قد سمعت بمقولة "غذاء للفكر".
Well, this is literally thought for food.
حسنا، هذا حرفياً فكرة للغذاء .
It finally is the right idea at the right time.
إنها أخيراً الفكرة الصائبة في الوقت المناسب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Très magnifique.
رائع جداً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)